<metadata><eainfo><overview><eaover>HSG_SCALE: classifies land based on 1934 map</eaover></overview></eainfo><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Metropolitan Council</origin><title>Historic Home Owners' Loan Corporation Neighborhood Appraisal Map</title><pubinfo><publish>Metropolitan Council</publish></pubinfo><pubdate>20160526</pubdate><onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-plan-historic-holc-appraisal</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>In 1934, the Federal Housing Administration created a financial mortgage system that rated mortgage risks for properties based on various criteria but was centered on race and ethnicity. This rating system propagated racial segregation that in many ways persists today.

The FHA Underwriting Handbook incorporated color-coded real estate investment maps that classified neighborhoods based on assumptions about a community, primarily their racial and ethnic composition, and not on the financial ability of the residents to satisfy the obligations of a mortgage loan. These maps, created by the Home Owners Loan Corporation (HOLC) were used to determine where mortgages could or could not be issued. 

The neighborhoods were categoriezed into four types:
Type A : Best - newer or areas stil in demand
Type B : Still Desirable - areas expected to remain stable for many years
Type C : Definitely Declining - areas in transition
Type D : Hazardous - older areas considered risky

Neighborhoods shaded red were deemed too hazardous for federally-back loans. These "red-lined" neighborhoods were where most African American residents lived. 

Many have argued tha the HOLC maps institutionalized discriminating lending practices which not only perpetuated racial segregation but also led to neighborhood disinvestment. Today, neighborhoods classified as Type C and Type D in 2934 make up the majority of neighborhoods in 2016 that are Areas of Concentrated Poverty where 50% or More are People of Color. 
</abstract><purpose>Representing this historic map in digital form allows users to compare historically characterized neighborhoods in relation to current demographic trends.</purpose><supplinf>Minneapolis and Saint Paul, Minnesota</supplinf></descript><crossref><citeinfo><title>Areas fo Concentrated Poverty, Areas of Concentrated Poverty where 50% or more are People of Color</title></citeinfo></crossref><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>19340101</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>None Planned</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-94.012</westbc><eastbc>-92.732</eastbc><northbc>45.415</northbc><southbc>44.471</southbc></bounding></spdom><accconst>None. This dataset is public domain under the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13). If the dataset is not available from the Online Linkage in Section 6, please contact the Distribution Contact Person.</accconst><useconst>None. This dataset is public domain under the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).</useconst><keywords><theme><themekey>Areas fo Concentrated Poverty, Areas of Concentrated Poverty where 50% or more are People of Color</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Minneapolis, St. Paul</placekey></place></keywords><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Paul E. Hanson</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1642</cntvoice><cntemail>paul.hanson@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><distinfo><distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab><stdorder><ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Paul E. Hanson</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1642</cntvoice><cntemail>paul.hanson@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20160609</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Paul E. Hanson</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1642</cntvoice><cntemail>paul.hanson@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><dataqual><lineage><procstep><procdesc>This data was digitized from a non-georeferenced, photgraphic image of the original map. Categorization and descriptions are composites from multiple sources.

</procdesc></procstep></lineage><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>This data was digitized from a non-georeferenced, photgraphic image of the original map. The accuracy is unknown.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc></dataqual><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>